<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
  <!ENTITY appversion "2.6">
  <!ENTITY manrevision "2.6">
  <!ENTITY date "Feb 2004">
  <!ENTITY app "<application>GNOME Robots</application>">
  <!ENTITY appname "GNOME Tali">
  <!ENTITY version "2.6">
]>

<article id="index" lang="da">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>GNOME Robotter Dokumentation</title>

    <copyright>
      <year>2001</year>
      <holder>Patanjali Somayaji, Mark Rae</holder>
    </copyright>

    <publisher> 
      <publishername>GNOME Documentation Project </publishername>
    </publisher>
  
    &legal;
  
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>&appname; Manual V&manrevision;</revnumber>
        <date>&date;</date>
        <revdescription>
          <para>Converted from the original HTML by Callum McKenzie, who doesn't speak Danish.</para>
        </revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  
    <releaseinfo>This manual describes version &appversion; of &appname;.
    </releaseinfo>
    <legalnotice>
      <title>Feedback</title>
      <para>To report a bug or make a suggestion regarding this game or
      this manual, follow the directions in the <ulink
      url="ghelp:gnome-feedback" type="help">GNOME Feedback Page</ulink>.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>


  <indexterm zone="index">
    <primary>GNOME Robots</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect1 id="Introduction">
    <title>Introduktion</title>
    <para>
    Gnome Robotter er en udvikling af det originale Gnome Robot spil, som
was itself based on the tekst baserede robot spil, som kan findes
on a number of UNIX systems, and comes with the BSD games package on Linux
systems.
    </para>
    <para>
    This new version includes two types of robots, movable junkheaps, 
multiple game configurations, user definable keyboard layouts, sound using 
ESD if you have it, as well as all of the other features which were present 
in the original Gnome Robots game.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="Play">
    <title>Spillet</title>

    <para>
When you start the game you will find yourself surrounded by a number of
robots, or some other strange but equally hostile adversaries if you have
chosen a scenario other than the default.</para>

<para>As you move about, the robots will move directly towards you with one 
goal in mind - killing you. As if that wasn't bad enough there are two types 
of robots, one of which can move twice as fast as you!</para>
<para>Luckily you have two ways to avoid this unfortunate outcome.</para>

<para>Firstly, the robots have not been blessed with a great deal of intelligence,
and will be destroyed if they crash into each other, or any other debris
which has been left around from previous collisions.</para>
<para>Secondly, if you do find yourself in a tight spot, you have the ability
to teleport randomly to another spot on the screen.</para>
<para>And, if supported in the game configuration you have chosen, you can 
push the junkheaps around to form barricades to protect you. Also if you are
daring enough you can Splat! the robots by pushing junkheaps on top of them
for an additional bonus.
    </para>

<para>
Unfortunately, randomly teleporting means that there is a chance that
you might end up being right next to a robot so they can kill you when
they make their move. All is not lost however, as you can have a number of
safe teleports which will place you out of immediate danger. You can earn
more free teleports as you go along, how you gain them depends on the 
chosen game, but typically you get one for each robot that is
destroyed while you are 'waiting', up to a maximum of 10. If you don't
want to waste your saved up safe teleports you can choose to randomly
teleport if you think it's safe enough.</para>

<para>If you press the 'Wait' key (see below) you will no longer be able to
move until either all of the robots, which still move towards you, are
gone or you are killed. Doing this may earn you extra safe teleports
as described above.</para>

<para>If you manage to reach the point where more than half of the screen is
occupied by robots, the number of robots will be reset to the starting amount,
allowing you to continue.</para>

  </sect1>
 
  <sect1 id="kbd">
    <title>Keys</title>


      <sect2 id="set3-keys">     
      <title>
        The Keypad
      </title>
      <para>
        When you select this set, you use the numeric keypad on the
        right hand side of the keyboard (not the separate arrow keys).
        <note>
        <title>Switch on the NumLock Key</title>
          <para>
            You may need to switch on the NumLock to make these work.
          </para>
        </note>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem><para>
            Up Left: <keycap>7</keycap>
          </para></listitem> 
          <listitem><para>
            Up: <keycap>8</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Up Right: <keycap>9</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Left: <keycap>4</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Stand Still: <keycap>5</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Right: <keycap>6</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Down Left: <keycap>1</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Down: <keycap>2</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Down Right: <keycap>3</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Teleport: <keycap>+</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Ramdomly Teleport: <keycap>-</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Wait: <keycap>Return</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
        </orderedlist>

      </para>	  
    </sect2>

  <sect2 id="set2-keys">	
      <title>
      Left Hand Keys 
      </title>
      <para>
         These keys are laid out on the left hand side of the keyboard.
      </para>
    <orderedlist>
          <listitem><para>
            Up Left: <keycap>Q</keycap>
          </para></listitem> 
          <listitem><para>
            Up: <keycap>W</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Up Right: <keycap>E</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Left: <keycap>A</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Stand Still: <keycap>S</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Right: <keycap>D</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Down Left: <keycap>Z</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Down: <keycap>X</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Down Right: <keycap>C</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Teleport: <keycap>T</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Ramdomly Teleport: <keycap>R</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Wait: <keycap>Return</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
        </orderedlist>




      </sect2>

    <sect2 id="standard-keys">

    <title>
    Original Keys 
    </title>
    
    <para>
      These keys are the controls used in the original robots
      game. They will be familiar to people who have played other
      older text-based games.
    </para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
	  <para>
            Up Left: <keycap>Y</keycap>
	  </para>
          </listitem> 
          <listitem><para>
            Up: <keycap>K</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Up Right: <keycap>U</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Left: <keycap>H</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Stand Still: <keycap>.</keycap> or <keycap>space</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Right: <keycap>L</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Down Left: <keycap>B</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Down: <keycap>J</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Down Right: <keycap>N</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Teleport: <keycap>T</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Ramdomly Teleport: <keycap>R</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>
            Wait: <keycap>W</keycap>	      
          </para></listitem>
        </orderedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="defining">
  <title>Definér dine egne</title>
  <para>Of course if you don't like any of the above keyboard layouts you can
define your own. Select the box for the required movement and the press
the key you want, the text representation of that key should then appear
in the box.</para>
  </sect2>      

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="preferences">
    <title>Præferencer</title>

<para>The properties dialog allows you modify the behaviour and appearance of
the game. There are three pages to the dialog:</para>

<sect2 id="configuration">
<title>Konfiguration</title>
<para>This page allows you to choose the type of game you want to play.
The drop-down box at the top of the page allows you to choos from a number of 
predefined games, and the list-box below it shows the settings for that
game.</para>
<para>The safe moves option will help you to avoid being killed due to a mistake.
If you try to make a move that would lead to your death when there is a safe 
move available you will not be allowed to procceed. But be warned if there
was no safe move available, other than teleporting, the move will be allowed 
to proceed.</para>
<para>There is also a ``super safe mode''.  If you select this, you get
beeped when there is no safe move and your only option is to teleport out.
</para>
<para>If you select the sound check-box the game will play sounds for various
events throughout the game. If you do not have ESD installed the game will
beep using the computer speaker only on invalid moves.</para>
<para>The 'Splats' checkbox selects whether you want and sound played and a small
'Splat!' to appear on the screen.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="graphics">
<title>Grafik</title>
<para>This page allows you to select the graphics used throughout the game from
the list in the dropdown-box. You will get a preview of the graphics 
below it.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="keys">
<title>Tastatus</title>
<para>This screen allows you to define your own keyboard controls as described
if the <link linkend="kbd">Keys</link> section.</para>
</sect2>

  </sect1>

<sect1 id="misc">
<title>Diverse</title>
<para>You can design your own graphics for the game if you want. The graphics
files are found in <filename class="directory">$PREFIX/share/pixmaps/gnobots2</filename>, where <filename class="directory">$PREFIX</filename> depends on where Gnome
was installed, usually either <filename class="directory">/usr</filename> or <filename class="directory">/usr/local</filename></para>
<para>Each character is 16x16 pixels and there are 14 of them arranged in
a PNG file which is 224x16 pixels in size. You can look at the existing
files to see the order in which they must be arranged to produce the correct
animated sequences.</para>
<para>Any graphics files which are placed in the directory are auto-detected
so you don't need to alter any configuration files.</para>
<para>
You can also define your own game configurations by creating extra
'.cfg' files which are stored in the <filename class="directory">$PREFIX/share/gnobots2</filename> directory.</para>

</sect1>

 <sect1 id="authors">
    <title>Authors</title>
    <para>
      <application>GNOME Robots</application> was written by Mark Rae
      (<email>m.rae@inpharmatica.co.uk</email>). Please send all comments, suggestions, and bug
      reports to the <ulink url="http://bugs.gnome.org" type="http">GNOME
      bug tracking database</ulink>.  (Instructions for submitting bug
      reports can be found <ulink
      url="http://bugs.gnome.org/Reporting.html" type="http">
      on-line</ulink>.)  You can also use <application>Bug Report
      Tool</application> (<command>bug-buddy</command>), available in the
      <guisubmenu>Utilities</guisubmenu> submenu of <guimenu>Main
      Menu</guimenu>, for submitting bug reports.
    </para>
   <para>
      This manual was written by Patanjali Somayaji
      (<email>patanjali@mindless.com</email>), from the original
      HTML documentation by Mark Rae. Please send all comments and
      suggestions regarding this manual to the <ulink type="http"
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gdp">GNOME Documentation
      Project</ulink> by sending an email to
      <email>docs@gnome.org</email>. You can also add your comments
      online by using the <ulink type="http"
      url="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gdp/doctable/">GNOME
      Documentation Status Table</ulink>.
    </para>
</sect1>
</article>

